Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair;
But I cannot sever the tangled threads on my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I see the Empress is also here.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Please rise.
Yes.
Peace to Imperial Mother.
Are you feeling better today, Imperial Mother?
I am.
The earth qi is cold.
Rise and have a seat.
I asked you to come because I have a request.
I obey your order, Imperial Mother.
I heard that Concubine Sourire is pregnant,
but you hesitate to bring her back due to the astrological signs.
This matter concerns the harem,
so I can't make a decision on my own.
Also, the Astrological Office said this
might endanger your well-being.
I'm advanced in age. My health is declining.
But what is more important than your heirs?
Do you agree, Empress?
Yes.
I don't think
the astrological sign of the Roof mansion is important.
The Empress and I have Heaven's great blessings
and we are not afraid.
But Emperor, have you been informed
that the Fourth Prince was almost poisoned last night?
He is too scared to return to his residence,
and I let him stay in my palace to watch over him.
If anything happens to Concubine Sourire's child,
you and I must no longer tolerate the offender.
Then I'd like to bring Concubine Sourire back right away.
Zhen is very blessed, becoming pregnant
from Your Majesty's first visit.
Her sisters in the palace will feel envious.
Moreover, Zhen was deprived of her title of Consort
and was considered banished.
This is known by everyone in the palace.
There is no precedent for a banished
concubine to return to the palace.
Titles can be conferred as well as banished.
If that is the concern, I will grant her a new title.
I'm afraid the civil officials will be critical of such a big change.
Imperial Mother, Concubine Sourire is bearing an imperial heir.
We can't leave her "hanging like laundry" in the mountains.
She should be brought back for a peaceful pregnancy.
You are the emperor.
You decide when and how she will return.
My current concern is the Fourth Prince;
I'm too ill to take care of him for long.
I hope you can arrange a foster mother for him.
If left on his own, he will be like
"a bird trembling over the bow twangs."
I understand.
And remember,
even though Concubine Sourire bears an heir,
don't overly favor her and make her
conceited over her status again.
I don't believe the Empress will oppose this arrangement.
I'm certainly glad that Zhen can return to the palace.
I miss her quite a lot.
The Goose Pear Bedside Incense requires a special technique.
First, weigh one tael of powdered agarwood
and one mace of powdered sandalwood.
Then remove the core of the goose pear
and pour the powder in.
Put the top of the goose pear back carefully.
Place the whole goose pear into this silver jar
and steam and chill it three times.
Come back to me once it's done.
Yes.
Please forgive me for not noticing Your Majesty's honoring presence.
Rise.
Yes.
I just came by to watch you making incense,
so I didn't ask them to announce my arrival.
If Your Majesty needs any incense,
you can have your servant send the order to me.
I will deliver the incense to Your Majesty myself.
I'm afraid the servants can't transmit my words clearly and correctly.
Then you might become confused
and even choke yourself from the smoke.
I hope Your Majesty can enlighten my dull-witted mind.
His Majesty insists on bringing Concubine Sourire back.
Do you have any incense that can change his mind?
I am incompetent.
Does Your Majesty have a plan?
What plan could I have?
His Majesty must have her back,
so I will let her come back.
Better to have her under my nose than out of my sight.
I suggested a new palace should be built
for Concubine Sourire the other day.
Have you decided yet?
I wish you hadn't mentioned it.
It makes me mad when it's brought up.
How is it that you feel this way?
Today ...
I brought this up in court,
and all the officials opposed it
as if they had planned to in advance.
They said that the Treasury is on a tight budget
due to the floods in the southwest.
and that we might lose popular support
if we undertook
large-scale construction for a consort.
"A huge speech about a trivial topic!"
The officials are always like that, fussing over small things.
It's Your Majesty's decision after all.
It'd be improper to go against all the officials.
I have decided
that the Household Department will refurbish
the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
I don't think the officials will oppose.
Just as well.
As long as Concubine Sourire won't feel aggrieved.
But their opinions
made me feel I need to put some further thought into this.
They oppose my decision to bring back a banished consort
saying that Zhen is the daughter of a guilty official
and is from the lower five Han banners.
They said she doesn't have a noble background nor given birth to a prince,
and that the gender of the child in her belly is still unknown.
Considering all this,
it does not seem like a good time
to bring Concubine Sourire back.
How about...
I've made up my mind.
She came from the lower five Han banners,
but I'll promote her
to the top three Manchu banners,
and grant her the surname Niohuru
of the prominent Manchu clan.
I hope Your Majesty will reconsider.
If Your Majesty would like to award Zhen a prestigious surname,
you could append "Jia" to her surname
so that her surname would be Zhenjia.
[Adding Jia to a surname is an honor.]
With her new surname, she is no longer
the daughter of the guilty official Zhen Yuandao.
She has no sons,
but there is also a prince who has no mother in the harem.
Does Your Majesty mean the Fourth Prince?
But the Fourth Prince is from a humble birth.
That's exactly why he needs a mother from a distinguished family.
From today on,
the Fourth Prince's mother is no longer the maid Li Jingui,
but my Consort Niohuru Zhen Huan.
But Concubine Sourire is only twenty-two years old
- just seven years older than the Fourth Prince.
How can she be the Fourth Prince's mother?
That's not difficult.
I will announce that Huanhuan left the palace to pray for the nation
after giving birth to the Fourth Prince.
Then she's not a banished consort.
As for her age, that's simple.
What harm would it do if I say she's thirty-two years old.
I'll agree if Your Majesty insists.
I'm just afraid that this won't stop the gossip.
What's there to be afraid of from gossip?
No matter if they gossip about it or not,
I am determined to give Huanhuan the title of Consort.
The name "Sourire" is not good.
It caused so many troubles in the past.
I will also change her honorary name.
The past is gloomy and cannot be retraced
but the path forward is full of brilliant light.
I will name her Lumière.
"The brilliant light."
What do you think?
It is excellent, Your Majesty.
Everything is ready in the palace.
Your Highness will be able to return in a few days.
His Majesty will promote Your Highness to Consort Lumière
and grant you the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Your Highness will also foster the Fourth Prince.
The Fourth Prince?
Yes.
Your Highness was a banished consort.
There was too much gossip about it outside the palace.
To sidestep these comments, His Majesty grants
Your Highness the surname Niohuru
and explains that you are the Fourth Prince's mother.
To make this believable, His Majesty
added ten years to your age .
So, thirty-two?
Our mistress doesn't look like thirty-two at all!
Of course not.
This is just to prevent any fodder for gossip.
These are trivial matters.
I appreciate His Majesty's decision.
His Majesty also said that
Peak Lingyun is too inadequate to live in.
Your Highness will be troubled to reside in
the Temple of Pure Dew for a few days.
And then Your Highness will return to the palace from the temple.
I will follow His Majesty's arrangements.
I don't suppose the Temple of Pure Dew will disagree.
Returning to the temple now -
I wonder how those petty snobs will react!
What a delight!
Mistress, why aren't you ready?
Su Peisheng will be here soon to deliver His Majesty's decree.
Jade, please do my hair.
Mistress, to return to the palace,
there are some things you must leave behind.
Including...
your heart.
This doesn't mean to have a cruel heart,
because that still implies feelings.
Your Highness must become
cruel
with no feelings in your heart at all.
Jinxi,
no one else
would say such things to me.
By the grace of Heaven,
His Majesty decrees:
"I praise the expanding prosperity of the palace"
"arising from the gentleness and kindness of the harem."
"Niohuru Zhen Huan, from the prestigious family Niohuru,
is distinguished by her dutifulness and decorum."
"At the Empress Dowager's benevolent behest,
I hereby grant her the title of Consort Lumière."
This is His Majesty's edict.
I thank His Majesty for the heavenly grace.
I congratulate Your Highness.
His Majesty selected a highly auspicious day for your conferral ceremony.
In three days a ceremonial envoy will arrive to
escort Your Highness back to the palace.
Thank you, Mr. Su.
Imperial Mother.
I was thinking to have Zhen back in a few days.
But the ceremonial envoy is not chosen yet.
Order the Ministry of Rites to select someone competent.
I believe she has been pregnant for three months already.
It's time for her to be properly attended to.
Your Majesty! Your Majesty!
He... He's back! He's back!
Look at you all flurried.
You can't even make a sentence.
Who is back?
Who is it?
Your Lordship!
Your Lordship, is it really you?
It's me. I'm back.
Is Mother here?
Yes. Yes.
Your Venerable Highness!
Mother!
Your Venerable Highness, look who is here!
- Mother!
- Yunli!
Peace to Mother.
Yunli.
Mother.
Yunli...
Is it really you?
It is me, Mother.
I just arrived - I came immediately.
Yunli...
They all said you died in the Yellow River.
I cried my eyes out for you.
Mother, don't be sad.
Look at me. I'm here safe and sound.
Right, I'm not sad.
I'm happy. I'm really happy.
By the way,
have you visited the Emperor and the Empress Dowager?
I heard that Her Majesty's health is worsening.
I sent Ajin to the palace as soon as we got back.
I rushed here to see you, Mother.
Yunli...
Now you are back...
But Huan'er...
is no longer here.
What do you mean, Mother?
Yunli,
Huan'er...
is going back to the palace.
Yunli, you must understand.
Perhaps Huan'er has some reasons she can't speak of.
We both thought...
that you were ...
you were gone.
But even though there were rumors,
Even if she had difficulties...
Huan'er is...
Yunli, aspirations differ from person to person.
Do not hate Huan'er.
One day,
you will know her hardship.
Mother,
I'm going to find her.
I need to ask her about all this!
Yunli! Yunli!
His Majesty's decree has been delivered.
I will never see the blue skies outside the palace.
Huan'er!
Your Lordship!
Huan'er, are you sitting here waiting for me?
Jade, today is a big day for Her Highness.
You shouldn't wet your dress with tears.
Go change into something festive.
Seeing Your Lordship return safely,
I must go offer incense to Buddha.
His Majesty's decree has been delivered.
There is no turning back.
If you let emotions hold sway now,
there will be endless troubles in the future.
"Her Highness"?
So it is true - you are going back to the palace.
I never expected that
I could witness Your Lordship's safe return in my lifetime.
"Your Lordship"?
After only four months,
everything has so quickly changed.
You are "Her Highness" again.
Perhaps because it's been so long since I heard you addressed like that
it feels distant.
I am glad you are back.
I wish I died back there in Tibet!
I wish I had never come back!
Huan'er.
It was the thought of you that helped me come back.
But the moment I return,
I have to watch you being escorted back to the palace,
back to my brother's side.
If you hadn't come back,
you would've assumed I was forever waiting for you.
you wouldn't have realized what a heartless woman I am.
I have always been this heartless woman!
Heart... less?
Heartless!
I'm ashamed of what I've done to Your Lordship.
There's no more to be said.
Please go back, Your Lordship.
Your Venerable Highness, Jade is here.
Grace to Your Venerable Highness.
What brings you here?
My Lady sent me to look for His Lordship.
What did Huan'er say?
Will it be safe to do so?
Yes, please don't worry, Your Lordship.
Good.
I will be waiting there at that time.
Your Lordship.
Take care.
Mother, I have to go...
Just go.
Your Venerable Highness, His Lordship is so sad.
Why don't you tell him the truth?
I also don't want to see him suffer like this.
But if I told him the truth,
given Yunli's temperament,
he would try to steal away with Huan'er no matter the cost.
And then the Emperor would know that
Huan'er is not pregnant with his child.
But now, I'm afraid His Lordship will be
deeply resentful towards Mistress Mochou.
Otherwise,
all our lives would be at stake.
At the moment,
we must choose the lesser of two harms.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
You finally wanted to see me.
Now that I see you've returned safely,
I can return to the palace with my mind at peace.
You came here only to tell me this?
What did Your Lordship think?
We were separated for so long,
and you haven't even asked where I was.
Does it matter whether I asked or not?
Now that I see you standing in front of me unscathed,
I have nothing left to worry about.
If you stopped worrying because I'm unharmed,
then you must have been worried about me day and night
when rumors were spoken about my death.
Am I right?
Truly your Lordship's heart is "as perceptive as seven hearts,"
but Your Lordship is using six hearts too many.
Our hearts already beat as one.
You're acting cold only because you have to
return to the palace all of a sudden.
Yunli,
our shared fate has come to an end.
Our fate?
You said you never believed in fate
when it comes to love and affection.
Fate is used as a pretense by the weak and spineless
who wouldn't even put up a fight!
You said “deeply shared fate” is an excuse to get attached to someone
and “we are not fated” is a pretense to end it.
I also said that
one day if I had nowhere to go and no future,
then I would say "It must have been fated."
I'm only here to tell you
that all I want is to end the affection between us.
Someone must have told you
that I'm three months pregnant.
Three months.
You should know that this child is not yours.
Yes, three months...
That must mean...
You reconciled with His Majesty only one month after I left.
At that time everyone believed that I was dead,
so you were not wrong to protect yourself.
But my heart aches for you...
Huan'er.
You came out of the palace with your heart dead.
Why are you returning to that heart-rending place
to have your mind exhausted again?
I can't bear to see that.
I would rather...
I would rather that Wen Shichu was the one
who would take care of you for the rest of your life -
at least he has a true heart for you.
Only His Majesty can grant me what I want.
My father's life,
a chance to live for the Zhen clan,
and a life of opulence and glory for me.
I've suffered enough cold shoulders and humiliation
these years at the Temple of Pure Dew.
I've had enough of "living like meat
between the knife and chopping board."
I don't believe that.
Opulence and glory?
How can your noble eyes be captured by that?
If you are using that excuse and belittling yourself,
then you also belittle my feelings for you.
The woman I love wholeheartedly
is not someone like this!
Your Lordship was deluded by your eyes!
I'm a mortal with earthly desires.
I want to live a good life.
I want people around me to live a good life.
I no longer want to be trampled upon!
On that day,
my ship sank in the Yellow River.
All my possessions were washed away.
If I hadn't been a good swimmer since childhood,
my corpse would be lying underwater right now.
I swam to the bank with great difficulty,
but was captured by Dzungar spies lying in ambush.
They took me from Longnan to Dzungar.
Do you remember the man
who we saved from snakebite in the mountain?
He's the eldest son of Dzungar's Khagan Tsewang.
His name is Galdan.
He was the one who ambushed my ship.
He recognized who I was and treated me generously.
One day I stole his horse and escaped.
I didn't want you to worry about me.
I rode day and night so I could see you and Mother sooner.
Yunli...
Huaner,
it's not too late.
Come away with me.
I can abandon my wealth and imperial identity,
and as commoners we can live as husband and wife.
The child in your belly...
I'll treat him just like my own.
It is too late.
Yunli,
in this world, we can't live for our love alone.
The imperial decree has been delivered.
If we left together,
everyone around us would be implicated.
We can't be so selfish
and sacrifice them for our own sake.
I can't do that.
Neither can you.
If it were possible to go with you,
I would gladly leave everything behind.
But if we acted so willfully，
you know what would happen
to the lives of our parents and clans!
Calamities would drown them like a sweeping flood!
In all the vastness under Heaven,
there is not a place for Yunli and Zhen Huan.
We don't have other choices.
Huan'er,
If you ... the other day ...
when you spoke such ruthless words to me,
I didn't believe you.
But through your words today,
you made me realize that
you won't be by my side anymore.
We were separated for four months,
and things changed "like the blue sea turned into mulberry fields."
Huan'er, can I hold you one more time...
for just a moment?
From today,
I could hold anyone else in the world,
but I'll never
have you in my arms again.
Yunli,
being with you is a beautiful dream I dreamt.
How I wish I could never wake from this dream.
All the happiest days of my life are in this dream.
You gave them to me.
For me ...
Isn’t it the same?
All right, Huan’er.
Hearing this from you...
I will have no regrets in this life.
Find a girl who treats you with a true heart
and support each other, and grow old and gray together.
You will have a very good life together.
You will be happy all your life.
Are you saying this...
to try and pierce my heart?
All I've ever possessed
was written in our marital horoscope.
You are my everything.
There will be no one else.
Your Majesty, Nobel Prince Guo has returned.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise immediately.
Take a seat.
All is good now that you are back.
Very good.
When I heard that you died in the Yellow River,
it saddened me extremely.
Imperial Mother has been ill in bed.
This also kept her unsettled day and night.
Your return is Heaven's blessing on the Great Qing.
It is a blessing from Your Majesty
that Heaven allowed me to retrieve my life.
You came back just at the right time.
I have a happy event,
but I didn’t know who should help me.
I obey Your Majesty's command.
I am going to have Consort Lumière return to the palace.
She used to hold the title Consort Sourire.
Others were in a hurry to refute me when they heard this.
You seem quite composed.
Your ... Your Majesty bringing your beloved back to the palace...
is reasonable.
Besides, I also heard that
Consort Lumière is pregnant.
You sure have good sources!
Consort Lumière was a banished consort.
There is a lot of gossip outside.
I require someone of high status
to act as ceremonial envoy and escort her back to the palace.
But all the elder state princes have declined.
I can only ask you.
Would it bring more honor to Consort Lumière
if I were the envoy?
If not, I wouldn't ask you.
I understand the matter.
As long as it's for ...
Your Majesty, I am willing to be the envoy.
You are truly my good brother.
Then tomorrow
you will go with a unit half the size of the Empress's honor guards
to welcome Zhen back to the palace.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I heard His Majesty is sending a unit half the size of Your Majesty's honor guards
to bring Zhen back to the palace.
She is already named Niohuru.
His Majesty, to avoid gossip,
has raised her to the Bordered Yellow Banner
and conferred the distinguished surname Niohuru.
He also states she is the mother of the Fourth Prince,
and explains her absence as praying
for the nation at the Temple of Pure Dew.
She gets a son out of nowhere
and even got into the upper three banners.
Now her Palace of Eternal Longevity has been
appointed with inexhaustible luxury.
One could only stare at it astonished.
But the Fourth Prince is close to her age.
How could they become mother and son?
If His Majesty can claim she has a son,
he can certainly also add ten years to her age.
Your Majesty, do we really not have another way
to stop her from coming back?
What's bad about her coming back?
Although "all lands under Heaven belong to the Emperor,"
the harem is solidly in my hands.
She may come back if she wishes.
I can't compare to the wisdom of Your Highness.
But Concubine An,
you are very familiar with Zhen Huan's temperament.
You must take advantage of that.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Concubine Délice, you have to urge your father
to "keep their teeth on" Zhen Huan's return.
Throw mud at Zhen Huan whenever possible
to damage her reputation.
Your Majesty requested extensive repairs
to the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
The officials think it is because His Majesty
unjustly favors Zhen Huan.
Rumors have already been rampant.
You must spare no effort on this.
Any service to His Majesty during this time
will be assigned to Concubine An.
Yes.
The phoenix coronet and golden gown
are thousands of chains on me,
locking away all the happiness in my life.
You won't feel so bad once you're used to it.
Let's go outside.
Your Lordship.
Noble Prince Guo bows before Consort Lumière.
Your Highness, please embark
to the carriage waiting outside the temple.
Noble Prince Guo, please rise.
The fallen petals rest on Your Lordship...
The petals are already wilted.
They are not fitting to taint Your Lordship.
The falling petals also have human feelings.
Why brush them away?
Jade.
It seems we forgot the Her Highness's ruyi pendant.
Let's go inside and look for it.
Huan'er hopes Your Lordship
will someday be surrounded by many grandchildren
and enjoy prolonged happiness and longevity.
Without you,
happiness and longevity are a void,
beyond the Gate of Emptiness.
I'm here to escort Your Highness back to the palace,
to honor His Majesty's celestial grace.
Su Peisheng bows in respect before
Your Highness Consort Lumière.
I humbly bid Your Highness Consort Lumière goodbye.
Please, Your Highness.
Mr. Su, please allow me a moment.
I still have some trivial matters.
Prioress Jingbai.
Yes,
Your Highness.
During my years of Buddhist practice here,
I have to thank you for your care.
All Buddha’s disciples should practice compassion.
Your Highness...
Your Highness need not thank me.
Your "help" in former days
will not be forgotten even in my toothless days.
I will repay you.
Abbess Jingan.
Your Highness.
My grudges do not prevent me from feeling gratitude.
I will gratefully remember your help during my time here.
Jinxi.
Take these two copies of the Taiping Scripture that I copied down
to Abbess Jingan.
Yes.
I know gold or silver could never be to your liking.
The scripture is a small token of my appreciation.
I‘m gratefully honored, Your Highness.
But I still have an unfulfilled wish.
I hope Your Highness will allow it.
I understand what you are trying to say, Madam Abbess.
I will spare her despicable life.
I hope she can resolve to rectify her mistakes
and devote her whole heart to Buddha.
I humbly thank Your Highness for the grace.
I am grateful for Your Highness's benevolence.
Buddha will bring blessings to Your Highness.
Where is Moyan?
The humble nun Moyan is here, Your Highness.
Abbess Jingan acts as the head of nuns,
but her heart can be overly soft with benevolence.
From today on,
you will take over Jingbai's position as the Abbess's Assistant
and rectify the practices at the Temple of Pure Dew.
Yes.
Jingbai.
Yes, Your Highness.
What do you think about my arrangement?
Your Highness makes an enlightened judgment.
I'm humbly incompetent.
I should have renounced my position to the talented.
From now on,
Prioress Moyan will be the Abbess's Assistant.
You all should obey her discipline without defiance.
I follow Your Highness's guidance.
Jingbai
is exempt from death but her life will not go unpunished.
She framed me for stealing the bird's nest.
I shall reward her twenty lashes
as a warning to others.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.